Guide to the Christine Drennon European lantern slide collection, 1930s-1950
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center.
Christine Drennon European lantern slide collection
1930s - 1950
C0068
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
1.0 linear feet (2 boxes)
This collection contains lantern slides with images and maps of European cities in countries such as the Netherlands, France, Germany, Austria, Switzerland, and Italy.
University of Michigan
University of Texas
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Christine Drennon in 2002.
Biographical Information
Christine Drennon is an associate professor of sociology and anthropology at Trinity College in San Antonio, Texas. Drennon specializes in urban geography, particularly urban fragmentation and the consequent social reproduction of race, class, ethnicity, and gender relationships. Drennon received her Ph.D. from the University of Texas, Austin. Previously, she taught as an assistant professor of geography at George Mason University.
Scope and Content
The Christine Drennon European lantern slide collection contains 106 glass lantern slides from the Universities of Texas and Michigan. The collection consists of images and maps of pre and post-war Europe, including the Netherlands, France, Germany, Austria, Switzerland, and Italy. A large portion of the slides depict images and plans of polders - areas reclaimed from lakes and seas by the construction of a series of dams and dikes. Several slides reference historically significant events such as the 1945 inundation of the Wieringermeer - a polder in the northern Netherlands - by Nazi troops. Images show the Wieringermeer before, during, and after inundation. Images also include plans for the reconstruction of dams and the subsequent annexation of German territory awarded as reparations at the end of World War II. The collection also includes a number of images of urban and rural destruction as a result of World War II bombing campaigns across Europe. The rest of the collection includes images of city development, rural farming practices, industrial factories, and some monuments and areas of historical interest. All of the images and slides originate from the 20th century.
Arrangement
The collection was previously arranged into four series. The collection is currently arranged in its previous order without series.
Alternative Form Available
Digitized versions of these items can be found here:.
Related Material
Special Collections Research Center holds other collections pertaining to Europe and World War II. It holds other collections containing glass lantern slides, such as the and the It also holds other early photography collections, such as the
Aerial photographs--Europe.; Amsterdam (Netherlands)--Slides.; Austria--Slides.; Cities and towns--Europe--Slides.; Europe--Geography--Slides.; Geneva (Switzerland)--Slides.; IJssel Lake (Netherlands)--Slides.; Lantern slides--Europe.; Le Havre (France)--Slides.; Longwy (France)--Slides.; Netherlands--Slides.; Piazza San Marco (Venice, Italy)--Slides.; Polders--Netherlands--Slides.; Rotterdam (Netherlands)--Slides.; Sparti (Greece)--Slides.; Strasbourg (France)--Slides.; Tyrol (Austria)--Slides.; Venice (Italy)--Slides.; Wieringermeer--Slides.; World War, 1939-1945.; Zurich (Switzerland)--Slides.
Contents List
- "Toward Integration of Europe" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Political map of Europe and international alliances
- "East Central Europe - The Shatter Belt" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Map of the distribution of coal, petroleum and iron in central Europe
- Map of Europe, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Map of Europe grouping countries together by geographic location
- World map with Europe highlighted, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Map of the world with Europe highlighted
- "'Marshall Plan in Action' Trip to W. Europe" map, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Political map of Europe showing planned railroad improvements as part of the Marshall Plan
- "The Dutch-German Boundary Changes - 1949" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Political map of Europe showing the planned boundary changes for the annexation of German territory by the Netherlands
- "The Dutch-German Boundary Changes - 1949" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "The Dutch-German Boundary Changes - 1949" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "The Dutch-German Boundary Changes - 1949" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "The Dutch-German Boundary Changes - 1949" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "The Dutch-German Boundary" map - 1950, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "The Dutch-German Boundary 1559 - 1948" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Political map of the Dutch-German boundary from 1559
- "Site and Situation of the Vienna Basin" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Political map of Austria showing the geographic attributes of the Vienna Basin
- "Austria in Central Europe" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Map of Austria in central Europe
- "Austria Romana, 300 A.D." map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Map of Roman Austria with military maneuvers
- "Colonisation Through Conversion 750-795, 810-900, After 955" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Map of religious conversion in Austria during the 8th, 9th and 10th century
- Holland - 1300 map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Map of 14th century Holland
- Holland - 1600 map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Map of 17th century Holland
- "General Map of the Netherlands", circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Map of the Netherlands showing polders and future irrigation plans
- "General Map of the Netherlands" - "Netherlands and future plans", circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Netherlands reclaiming project - IJsselmeer map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Map of northern Netherlands detailing plans for IJsselmeer lake and polders
- Netherlands reclaiming project - IJsselmeer map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Map of the Netherlands - reclaimed land - 1947, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Map of reclaimed lands in the Netherlands
- Dinxperlo, Netherlands - "Demarcation Commission 1949" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  French map of the old and new boundaries of Germany and the Netherlands in the town of Dinxperlo
- Losser, Netherlands - "Demarcation Commission, 1949" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 25)
  French map of the old and new boundaries of Germany and the Netherlands in the town of Losser
- Sittard, Netherlands - "Demarcation Commission" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  French map of the old and new boundaries of Germany and the Netherlands in the town of Sittard
- "Westerwoldche" Westerwolde, Netherlands - "Demarcation Commission, 1949" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 27)
  French map of the old and new boundaries of Germany and the Netherlands along the Westerwolde canal
- "The Zuerderzee Before the Closing" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Map showing the depth of the Zuyderzee before enclosing with dikes
- Wieringermeer, Netherlands - polder map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Plan of the Wieringermeer polder
- Wieringermeer, Netherlands - polder map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 30)
- "Polder Dike - Enclosing Dam" diagram, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Cross section of a polder dike and dam
- "Netherlands: 1945 Inundation", circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Aerial view of land inundated by water
- "Netherlands: Hothouses", circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Aerial view of hothouses
- "Holland" - windmill, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Dutch windmill with attached buildings and land
- "Netherlands: Flooded area", circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Flooded rural building
- "Netherlands: Amsterdam", circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Buildings along a canal in Amsterdam
- "Lely Pumping Station Near Medemblick" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Aerial photograph of the Lely pumping station
- "Leiden, Holland, 1948", circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Bikers riding near a small bridge over a Leiden canal
- "Part of IJssel Lake" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 39)
  Part of IJssel Lake reclaimed for farm land
- "Middenmeer" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 40)
  Aerial view of farm plots and small community in Middenmeer
- "A village in the Wieringermeer" - "Middenmeer 1938, [19]45, [19]47" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 41)
  Images of Wieringermeer before, during, and after inundation
- "Rotterdam, 1939" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 42)
  Aerial photograph of Rotterdam with view of the Nieuwe Maas, a distributary of the Rhine River
- "Rotterdam 1939" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 43)
  Aerial photograph of Rotterdam with view of Rotterdam Centraal railway station
- "Rotterdam 1939" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 44)
  Aerial photograph of Rotterdam with view of city hall
- "Rotterdam 1946 - Townhall" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 45)
  Aerial photograph of Rotterdam with view of city hall after the Rotterdam Blitz
- "Rotterdam 1948" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 46)
  Aerial view of Rotterdam
- "Rotterdam 1948" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 47)
- "Dry dock - Rotterdam, 1948" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 48)
  Dry dock in Rotterdam
- "Urkerland Polder" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Aerial view of the Urkerland polder
- "Dike w. Rd [?] Holland and Friesland" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 50)
  Cars driving on road built on a dike in Friesland with people standing in foreground
- "Wieringermeer - fertile land" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 51)
  Aerial view of farm plots in Wieringermeer
- "Wieringermeer: 1st ploughing" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 52)
  Farmer ploughing reclaimed land in Wieringermeer
- "Netherlands: Reclaimed Land 1948 - Wieringermeer", circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 53)
  Farmer assessing crop on farm land
- "1945 - Wiedemeer polder" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 54)
  Flooded building
- "The Wieringermeer. Before, during, and after the intentional flooding by the Germans in April 1945" - Netherlands, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 55)
  Images of Wieringermeer before, during, and after the intentional inundation of the polder by German troops
- "Austria: Austrian - Italian Border, s. of Villach", circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 56)
  Men and guards at the crossing of the Austrian-Italian border, south of Villach
- Alpbach, Tyrol (Tyrol), Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 57)
  Buildings in Alpbach
- Brenner Pass, Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 58)
  "Brenner Pass from the north showing the gentle slope to the watershed"
- Roman city of Petronell-Carnuntum, Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 59)
  Roman ruins of the Heidentor of Carnuntum in present day Petronell
- "Austria: Road to Grossglockner tow. S", circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 60)
  View of the road to the Grossglockner (mountain) in the Austrian Alps
- Gosau Lake, Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 61)
  View of Gosau Lake (Gosaulacke) facing south towards Dachstein
- Perchtoldsdorf, Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 62)
  View of the parish church in the marktgemeinde (Market Town) of Perchtoldsdorf
- "Frankish Farm Near St. Poelten, Lower Austria (Vierkanter)", circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 63)
  View of road and farm building
- Schrattenthal from Schneeberg, Lower Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 64)
  Aerial view of the town of Schrattenthal from Schneeberg
- Salzburg, Austria - facing west, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 65)
  View of Salzburg looking towards Fortress Hohensalzburg
- Church ceiling, Tyrol, Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 66)
  Church ceiling in Matrei in OstTyrol, Tyrol. Possibly a detail of a fresco series by Franz Anton Zeiller done for the parish church of Matrei in OstTyrol, 1783
- Tyrol, Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 67)
  Aerial view of building and hills in Tyrol
- Courtyard, Weissenkirchen, Lower Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 68)
  Courtyard of a large estate in Weissenkirchen
- Group of people in Austrian folk costumes, New York City, NY, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  People in Austrian folk costume dancing in New York City in front of "International House"
- "Austria - Establishment of Eastern Boundary" map, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 70)
  Map of the eastern boundary of Austria
- Velden am Worthersee, Carinthia with view of Karawanks mountains, Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 71)
  View of Velden am Worthersee, including Velden Bay
- "The Old and New Abbey of Melk on the Danube," Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 72)
  View of Melk Abbey in background and the ruins of old Melk Abbey in foreground, separated by the Danube River
- Erzberg mine, Eisenerz, Styria, Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 73)
  Mining equipment and view of valley below
- Hydroelectric dam, Kaprun, Salzburg, Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 74)
  View of the dam and mountains beyond
- Hafelekarspitze (mountain), Innsbruck, Austria, 1933, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 75)
  Buildings near and onlookers near the Hafelekarspitze
- "Roman Road Across the Central Alps" - Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 76)
  View of the Roman Road through trees
- Farmers - Tyrol, Austria, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 77)
  Farmers working on a hill in Tyrol
- Danube River bend North towards Vienna, Kobenz, Austria, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  View of Kobenz next to the Danube River, facing North towards Vienna
- Port of Le Havre, France, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  View of dock in Port of Le Havre with cranes and automobiles
- Longwy, France, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  View of Longwy with steel factory in background
- Interior of Longwy steel factory, France, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Interior of Longwy steel factory, featuring furnaces and equipment
- Abandoned Maginot Fort in Northern Frances, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  View of abandoned Maginot Fort
- Genissiat Dam, France, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  View of Genissiat Dam
- Phosphate plant, Mulhouse, Alsace, France, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Damaged phosphate plant after air attacks in 1944
- "Le Bain aux Plantes" (Herbal Bath) in Strasbourg, France, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Buildings bordering a canal
- View from a schlucht (chine) from top of Vosges Mountains towards Lorraine, France, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  View from chine in Vosges Mountains with view of valley, river, and roads below
- Steel plant in Ruhr, Germany, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Steel plant machinery and equipment
- Cologne, Germany, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Cologne after bombing with view of the Cologne Cathedral
- Mill - West Midlands, England, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  View of mill and industrial sprawl in the "Black Country" of England
- Coal mining town of Cannock Chase, England, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  View of Cannock Chase buildings
- Clent Hills, West Midlands, England, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Aerial view of Clent Hills
- Gondolas on canal, Venice, Italy, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Gondoliers, gondolas, and passengers on Venetian canal
- Gondoliers rowing in canal, Venice, Italy, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Gondoliers rowing on Venetian canal, possibly in front of Piazza San Marco
- Piazza San Marco and gondolier, Venice, Italy, circa 1930s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  View of Piazza San Marco, including the Campanile, from the Venetian Lagoon with gondolier in foreground
- Zurich, Switzerland, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  View of Zurich and the Limmat river
- Geneva, Switzerland, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  View of Geneva, including Mont Blanc in background
- Mont Blanc, Switzerland, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 17)
  View of Swiss countryside with Mont Blanc in the background
- Temple of Artemis ruins, Sparta, Greece, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 18)
  View of "Oldest temple of (Artemis) Orthia at Sparta"
- Farmer operating mechanical digger, Europe, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Farmer tilling field with mechanical digger in unknown European location
- "Mechanical Trenching," Europe, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Aerial view of fields tilled via mechanical trenching in unknown European location
- Reconstruction of West Embankment, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Destroyed dike or dam, possibly in Wieringermeer, Netherlands
- Windmills, Holland (?), circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Aerial view of three windmills, likely in Holland
- Unidentified European port, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 23)
  View of European port, likely in Netherlands
- Unidentified map, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Unidentified map, likely European
- Unidentified topographical map, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Unidentified topographical map, likely European
- Dutch polder, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 26)
  View of road on edge of polder, possibly Wieringermeer, Netherlands